Come on.
>> In January of 2012, the FBI called me at
home and said, "Can you come to the
Washington field office Thursday at
10:00?"
>> Okay.
>> I said, "Absolutely."
So, I went down to the Washington field
office
and they began asking me questions.
Well, I've spent my entire adult life
working with the FBI. So, the FBI needs
my help. I'm happy to help.
It wasn't until I was about an hour and
45 minutes into this interview that I
realized, wait a minute, they're
investigating me.
>> We need to be honest with you. and they
said, "Well, we need to be honest with
you. We're executing a search warrant on
your house right now as we speak, and
we're seizing all of your electronics."
>> What I experienced as a whistleblower
sends the most chilling of messages
about what the government can and I will
emphasize will do when one speaks truth
to and of power.
>> There is information that the public in
a functioning democracy has a right to
know. What does it do to your whole body
rails against it?
>> Wordless wiretapping torture. We only
know about that because of
whistleblowers.
>> I knew I could not remain silent.
If I remain silent, I'd be complicit to
the subversion of the Constitution.
If I remain silent as a senior executive
assigned to the National Security
Agency, I would be an accessory to a
crime. Historically, such people were
forced to choose between their
conscience and their career. But now the
stakes are much higher. They risk their
freedom and their lives.
>> I did not commit a crime. I am going to
trial and I'm going to prove myself
innocent.
I'm not the pushover that these guys
think I am. I'm I'm as tough as they are
and I'm going to fight.
[Music]
Wow.
Oh,
[Music]
Sorry, they're all medals.
>> John, did you get her?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Where's Max?
>> He's sleeping.
Sorry to wake you up, but it's dinner
time.
[Music]
In my heart, I believe I'm going to win.
My wife tells me every time I start to
feel a little depressed, "You have the
truth on your side."
And she's right.
I haven't done anything wrong. His name
is John Cury, CIA undercover officer for
15 years.
>> Did you feel comfortable with the
techniques?
>> Uh, frankly, no. And I elected to uh to
forgo the training.
>> I was the first CIA officer or former
CIA officer to confirm the use of
torture techniques against al-Qaeda
prisoners.
>> What is it like? Uh, you feel like
you're choking or drowning.
>> It was already in the news. The
Washington Post, for example, had
reported that the CIA had used torture
techniques and Human Rights Watch had
reported it and Amnesty International
had reported it. So, in the back of my
mind, I didn't think I was saying
anything new.
>> Would you call it torture?
>> Um, I had never been on television in my
life. I truly expected this to be a
10-minute interview that they whittle
down to 15 seconds. Instead, he asked me
about Abuazuba and about torture. And I
think that uh water boarding is probably
something that we shouldn't be in the
business of doing.
>> Why do you say that now?
>> Because we're Americans and we're better
than that.
>> That interview became a major
international story. I ended up getting
calls from every network in America. The
CIA filed a crimes report against me
saying I had leaked classified
information by admitting that
waterboarding had taken place. Thank
goodness that the Justice Department
said that it was not classified and
declined to pursue a case against me.
And I think it's good that we're having
a national debate about this. We should
be debating this and Congress should be
talking about it because I think as a
country we have to decide if this is
something that we want to do as a matter
of policy. With that interview, I became
a CIA dissident.
>> Whether I knew it or not, whether I
liked it or not, I was an outsider from
that day onward.
[Music]
I'm fighting to have my September 10th
country back.
It's a very, very dangerous direction.
the pendulum swung after 911 and instead
of swinging back to some kind of
equipoise, it just swung even further in
the direction of secrecy. Um, and that
includes overclassification, that
includes a crackdown on whistleblowers,
that includes secret signing statements,
it includes shutting down lawsuits with
the state secrets privilege. I mean,
there's a whole bevy of secrecy tactics
that the government uses.
Every time you bring up civil liberties
that have deteriorated or been tossed
out completely in the name of national
security, people think somehow you're
siding with the terrorists. Oh, you want
our country to suffer. Quite the
opposite. People want our country to
continue to live up to the ideals on
which it was founded.
It's not something you aspire to. This
is not a career goal to become a
whistleblower. It's not.
It doesn't matter if it's in the public
interest or not. They can they can
pjoratively say it's leaking,
unauthorized leaking.
So, whistleblowers, it's clear, have
become an endangered species, to say it
that way. And you have a government
who's decided that they need to become
extinct.
The last thing they want is people
spilling the beans on what the
government's doing under the rubric of
secrecy and national security behind the
scenes.
To use the espionage act, it it is the
harshest thing you can charge someone
with. They were sending deliberately
sending the strongest possible message.
They set the target. They put the
bullseye on me and said, "We're going to
make an example of him.
[Music]
I was born in Louisiana. My father was a
officer in the US Air Force.
But the bulk of my growing up was
actually in Vermont
and that's where I went to high school.
That's where I became a young adult.
I was born and raised in a small town in
western Pennsylvania, north of
Pittsburgh in Amish country. I always
had a fascination with international
affairs. I was an avid um ham radio
operator when I was a kid, for example.
>> I grew up in Columbia, Maryland.
I grew up in a a somewhat dysfunctional
family and therefore at a very young age
the concept of justice became very
central to me.
>> The attorney general had the authority
to authorize it. I remember sitting in
social studies class watching the
Watergate hearings
>> to authorize wiretapping and other
related activity. Seeing these
incredible violations of law and the
Fourth Amendment, high crimes and
misdemeanors as specified in the
Constitution. No one was above the law,
not even the president of the United
States of America.
>> I went to college in New England and law
school. I dreamed of working at the
Justice Department. You go into court
and you have the impromater of the
United States behind you and you get to
wear the white hat and you get to always
be on the right side of whatever you're
arguing. So when I got the job at the
Justice Department right out of law
school, for me that was my dream job.
>> I was mostly interested in the Middle
East because when I was in high school,
the Iran hostage crisis was ongoing and
I thought I'm going to go to George
Washington University. It's two blocks
from the White House.
>> I made a choice that I would join the
Air Force for a few years as a crypto
linguist. And a cryptologic linguist is
someone who listens to communications of
other countries in different languages.
And the country that I specialized in
was East Germany.
>> My adviser, it turned out, was
undercover as a professor. He was
actually a CIA officer acting as what
was then called a spotter. and he asked
me if I was interested in working at the
CIA. I said, "Sure, why not?" And I went
through the process and found myself at
the CIA.
>> I went to the CIA for a short stint and
then I became a government contractor,
system software engineering from mid89
all the way through until 2001.
February of 2001, I had just had me
going through the Sunday edition of the
Washington Post. And it's like, oh,
interesting. NSA was actually looking to
hire people in from the outside. Well,
it's the call to serve your country and
here is an opportunity at a very senior
level. So, I applied. I was offered a
position, took the oath to support and
defend the Constitution for the fourth
time. And the first day that I reported
to the National Security Agency to my
duty station uh was 9/11. I ended up
joining a newly created ethics unit
called the professional responsibility
advisory office. We were there to keep
you out of trouble rather than OPR, the
office of professional responsibility
that disciplines you when you do do
something bad. We were there to render
advice prospectively to help keep you
from doing something unethical. The
first couple of years were really
amazing to get to form and grow this
office. But after 911, there was
definitely a sea change.
There's pre 911.
There's post 911.
And what took place in those weeks and
months just after 9/11 established the
basis for everything else that happened.
Everything.
Everything changed in the intelligence
community on September 11th.
It took a few years for it to unwind and
much of what was going on inside the
country was done in absolute secrecy for
the first four plus years.
No one knew
we're going to kill all of them.
That was very much the feeling in the
CIA after September 11th.
Now, for many people, that wore off
after a period of time.
>> But for others inside the CIA, they
never lost that that feeling that that
belief that this was a war to the death,
that there was no gray area between
black and white.
>> There was a lot of cutting corners.
There were a lot of shortcuts going on.
There were a lot of creative gymnastics
going on. And that can be seen in in
like the torture memos and the reasoning
in those by my law school classmate John
U.
>> After 911, it became even more important
to say just to get all the data it could
no matter where it was. We just need it.
And I was told that we just need it,
Tom. We just need the data.
It was crisis.
But it became clear within a space of a
few days this was not a normal crisis. I
was in a meeting with
with the person I reported to said that
911 was a gift to NSA.
911 is a gift. We're finally going to
get all the money we've ever wanted from
Congress.
All of it and more.
That whole counterterrorism effort,
which was extraordinarily small prior to
911, all of a sudden grew by leaps and
bounds after 911. George Tennant who at
the time was the director of central
intelligence. He issued an intelligence
communitywide memo said whatever you got
in the labs prototype test bed put into
the fight cuz we need it. So I was
tasked to go out to the ends of NSA to
find those systems bring them to the
attention of senior leadership so we
could actually deploy them. One that I
brought to their attention shortly after
911 was called Thin Thread.
Thin Thread, I have to say, was an
extraordinary program. They had a system
ready for operational deployment well
prior to 911, which by the way had built
into it the FISA rules. It absolutely
protected US person information.
Absolutely.
Okay. It was designed that way. That
solution was rejected.
and I said, "Why is NSA rejecting the
thin thread solution?"
And I wasn't going to give up because I
knew something was a miss. I wrote a
formal memo expressing my my greatest
alarm. I also had informed her that I
was hearing very disturbing information
that NSA could be in probable violation
of FISA and the Fourth Amendment.
I had people who came to me in private
who were telling me, "Tom, why are we
taking equipment that we use to monitor
the communications of foreign nations
and turning on ourselves?"
I thought, "We can't surveil Americans
without warrants."
I was told, "You have a problem.
Speak to the office general counsel."
>> Yes. I have a phone conversation with a
senior attorney assigned officer
council.
>> Right.
>> Then I heard the following words.
NSA has become the executive agent for
the program. It's been reviewed by all
the attorneys.
The White House has approved it. It's
all legal.
As soon as he said, "It's all legal,"
the hair stood up on the back of my
neck.
What I didn't know at that time is that
NSA under General Michael V. Hayden had
entered into a secret agreement with the
White House. A very small number of
people even knew about it. But what's
crucial here is that equipment that was
traditionally forward foreign facing
outward facing was now being turned on
our own country.
That Pandora's box had been opened up.
We would now instrument the United
States of America and we would treat
this nation as the equivalent of a
foreign country for the purposes of
draget blanket electronic surveillance
on a vast scale.
When I was arrested, it was national
front page news. Uh Fox News even put on
their ticker, ex CIA officer gives
intelligence to al-Qaeda.
>> This morning, a former CIA officer is
accused of repeatedly leaking classified
secrets to reporters. Investigators say
he potentially put the lives of covert
officers at risk.
>> These are very serious charges for the
ex-CIA intel officer.
>> Prosecutors say he told three
journalists the role of a CIA officer in
the capture of a top al-Qaeda leader.
>> Abu Zabeda reportedly waterboarded more
than 80 times. A controversial
interrogation technique.
>> A senior person at the Heritage
Foundation called me a traitor in an
op-ed in the San Francisco Chronicle. I
I forced myself to read some of these
articles and in every one of these
articles, Jesseline Raak was quoted and
I thought, "Wow, this woman gets it."
That there's a difference between
leaking and whistleblowing. That what I
blew the whistle on was government
illegality.
And I thought, I have to meet this
woman.
You become a whistleblower by operation
of law when you make a disclosure that
you reasonably believe evidence is
fraud, waste, abuse, or illegality. When
you look in the dictionary and the
synonyms for whistleblower are things
like snitch, backstabber, there are all
these negative connotations that go with
you bucking the system. You're not a
team player. You're a traitor because
that is the ultimate label. What's even
more interesting is that they brought up
the word whistleblower.
>> I'm not a criminal defense lawyer. What
I do is represent whistleblowers and
often work in tandem with criminal
defense lawyers on these espionage act
cases.
>> Judge Brinkma specifically warned them
not to dump discovery on us on the eve
of the trial.
>> In Kuryaku's case, the government's
ticked off that he called water boarding
torture. that he revealed torture as a
program and not some rogue pastime
and that he wrote a book in which he's
very critical of CIA's torture and the
behavior of the FBI. That's what the
government's really mad about.
>> John Kiryak was a CIA intelligence
officer from 1990 to 2004. He is charged
with violating the Espionage Act by
passing classified.
>> A journalist called John and asked him
to confirm a name which he did which is
routinely done by former agency
officials.
And for that they charged him with the
Espionage and Intelligence Identity
Protection Act counts.
The Espionage Act is this arcane 1917
law that is meant to go after spies, not
whistleblowers. It was inconceivable
that you would use such a heavyhanded,
out of scope, arcane law to go after
someone. I thought we figured that out
40 years ago with Dan Ellburg and his
case
when Tom Drake was indicted under the
Espionage Act. I thought it was a
strange oneoff though 4 months later
Steven Kim an analyst at the State
Department was also indicted. At that
point, I looked back and realized that
Sky Shami Liitz the year before had
plead guilty, was under a different part
of the Espionage Act. But there were
starting to be a pattern.
When you look at the totality of it, you
have Shami Liwitz of the FBI contract
linguist, Tom Drake of the NSA,
Steven Kim of the State Department, Jeff
Sterling of the CIA,
John Kuryaku of the CIA, and Bradley
Manning Army. And you realize for Obama
to have six of these on his watch and
they are all of people who are in the
national security or intelligence
fields.
>> A breach at the nation's top security
agency.
>> A young army private is now being
formally charged in connection with
leaked video.
>> There are common threads of government
overreach, secrecy, and trying to cover
up some of our worst sins as a country.
Whether it was a war crime or whether it
was secret domestic surveillance or
whether it was torture.
>> Steven Jin Wu Kim accused of violating
the Espionage Act.
>> Charged with repeatedly leaking
classified secrets.
>> Leaking classified information.
>> Top secret information.
>> Disclosing classified information.
>> According to the federal indictment,
Thomas Drake was
>> It's the most serious charge that can be
leveled against an American. It's saying
you are an enemy of the state. Why use
that? To send a very chilling chilling
message to people to keep quiet.
[Music]
After September 11th, I became the chief
of counterterrorism operations in
Pakistan.
I was told on my first day to come up
with the standard operating procedure
for taking down a terrorist safe house.
So I I literally sat at a desk with a
legal pad thinking, well, how how am I
going to do this? What would what would
be the first thing I I would want to do
if I was going to take down a safe
house? Well, I would want it to be dark.
So, let's say 2:00 in the morning will
do it. So, I wrote 0200 at the top of
the page. And then little by little, I
came up with this plan. All right.
>> Finally, we got a report from
headquarters that Abu Zubeda was
somewhere in Pakistan. Now, at the time,
we thought that Abu Zubeda was the third
ranking person in al-Qaeda. And all we
knew was that he was somewhere in
Pakistan, but Pakistan's the size of
Texas. He made one mistake that allowed
us to narrow his location down to 14
different sites.
So, we brought in a large team from
headquarters, half CIA, half FBI. We
brought in weapons and electronics and
walkie-talkies and we hit all 14 sites
at exactly the same time and he happened
to be in one of the houses. He tried to
escape by jumping from the roof of his
house to the roof of the neighboring
house and the Pakistanis shot him three
times in the stomach, the groin and the
thigh. And he was very gravely wounded.
He was out of it for a day and a half
before he finally came out of a coma,
but I was the first person to speak to
him.
At first, he asked for a glass of red
wine
and then a couple hours later, he asked
me to smother him with a pillow.
Once he sort of had his bearings and he
realized, "Oh my god, the Americans have
me." He wanted to know what was going to
happen to him, where he was going to be
sent. He was he was very frightened. Um
I think of of the unknown. I didn't know
where he was going to go and I didn't
know that he was going to be tortured. I
didn't have a need to know.
He would recite poetry to me that he had
written.
He cried at the thought of, he said,
never knowing the joy of fatherhood,
never knowing the touch of a woman.
I remember telling him, "I should hate
you and I should want to kill you and I
don't." I said, "You're pathetic." I
mean, he was just a young guy. He wasn't
even 30 years old. And all he did was
cry. And I remember saying to a
colleague of mine, "This is the fearsome
al-Qaeda. this is what we've been so
worried about and so frightened of. It
was a revelation to me. They're just
guys. They're just, and not even that,
they're just young, illiterate guys that
had nothing else to do. And believe me
when I say 99% of them had never read
the Quran. They weren't true believers.
They they hadn't pledged feelalty to
Osama bin Laden. They just wanted to get
out of that village in Yemen and maybe
make a couple of bucks.
[Music]
It made me think the mission wasn't all
it was cracked up to be.
And then a colleague came in and said,
"Eadquarters is sending in a private jet
to pick him up and take him to his next
location."
At about 3:00 in the morning, we wheeled
him out. He was so upset he asked me to
hold his hand. He asked if we were going
to kill him, and I said, "No, no, we've
been looking for you for a long time. In
fact, I said, "You're going to get the
best medical care that the US government
has to offer."
And so the doctor gave him a shot of
demoral and it knocked him out and we
loaded him onto this private jet.
One of the guys who had flown out to
escort him to his onward location, got
off the plane. The guy was dressed
completely in black, black mask, black
hat, black sweater,
and he said my name. And he said,
"John." And I said, "Who are you?" And
he lifted up his mask and he was a
former supervisor of mine at
headquarters. And he said, "What are you
doing here?" And I said, "Oh, I'm chief
of counterterrorism." I said, "What are
you doing here?" He said, "I'm going to
take your prisoner onward."
He said, "Who is he anyway?" And I said,
"I'm sorry, man. You don't have a need
to know."
And I said, "Where are you taking him?"
And the guy said, "I'm sorry, man. you
don't have a need to know.
And I said, well, safe flight.
And the plane took off and I never saw
him again.
When I returned to headquarters from
Pakistan, I was told that the CIA had
begun a program that they were calling
enhanced interrogation techniques. And
did I want to be trained in the use of
these enhanced interrogation techniques?
Uh, I had a visceral problem with it.
First of all, let's call it what it is.
It's torture. They can they can call it
whatever euphemism they want, but it's
torture. So, I went back to the
counterterror center and I said, I have
a problem with this and I don't want to
be involved.
And then I heard rumors that we had
created this system of secret prisons
around the world. that even the heads of
state in these countries didn't know
that we had these secret prisons there.
That these were deals struck between the
head of the CIA and the head of whatever
that country's service was.
These weren't meant to be permanent
facilities. They were just meant to
extract information
where we didn't have to worry about laws
or human rights.
But, you know, those of us who weren't
read into these programs only got this
in bits and pieces.
I had no idea how extensive the secret
prison system was until a couple of
years after I left the agency and I read
about it in the press
because we're Americans and we're better
than that.
But at the time, you didn't feel that
way. At the time I was so angry and I
wanted so much to help disrupt future
attacks on the United States that I felt
it was the only thing we could do.
>> And with Zabeta, you think that was
successful?
>> It was. I had been misinformed by the
CIA.
>> The CIA told those of us in headquarters
that they had waterboarded Abu Zuba one
time that he had cracked and that he had
provided actionable intelligence. He
answered every question just like I'm
sitting here speaking to you.
>> So in your view, the water boarding
broke him.
>> I think it did. Yes.
>> And did it make a difference in terms of
>> It did. The threat information that he
provided disrupted a number of attacks,
maybe dozens of attacks. That turned out
to be untrue.
And we know it was untrue because in
2009, the CIA Inspector General's report
was released indicating that Abu Zubeta
had been waterboarded 83 times.
and still did not provide actionable
intelligence.
Believe me, for the life of me, I wish I
could take that back. But I talked about
the issue with the information that I
had at the time, and the information was
just simply incorrect.
Abuzza may never have been an al-Qaeda
member. Now, in retrospect, we're
finding out. He may have been somebody
who supported al-Qaeda's goals. He may
have been someone who was a professional
logistician where he was helping them
procure medicine or false documents. We
don't really know. But he was not the
senior al-Qaeda official that the CIA
and NSA and the White House wanted us to
believe.
>> So I actually like vac everything was
vacuumed out. I laid down this.
>> My husband was incredibly supportive.
>> And so I think that was a saving grace.
>> When all this horrible stuff was going
on, I could go home and there was sort
of this safe haven.
Bye.
>> You know, I promised myself when I was
going through this that if I ever got
out of this mess, I would dedicate my
life to representing whistleblowers.
whistleblowers
[Music]
come in here and they'll say to me, "You
will not believe what I'm going
through." And I can actually look them
in the eye and say, "Yes, I will." And I
do
because I know what the government's
capable of doing.
My becoming a whistleblower
began on December 7th of 2001.
And I got a call from the criminal
division saying that the FBI on the
ground in Afghanistan
had captured an American fighting with
the Taliban.
And my counterpart wanted to know, could
the FBI interrogate him without a
lawyer? And I was told unambiguously
that this American, a guy named John
Walker Lind, was represented by council.
Now, from my office, this was a
breadandbut kind of question. I said no.
Um, it would be a pre-indictment
interview of someone who was in custody,
and it was not an undercover operation.
I went home over the weekend not
thinking about it and I came back on
Monday and the gentleman from
counterterrorism called back and he
said, "Oops, we did it anyway." The FBI
went ahead and interrogated him. What do
we do now? You know, I was trying to
work with with the criminal division and
saying like, "Okay, look, I understand
you're on the battlefield, heat of war,
and they interrogated him anyway, so
let's figure out how to do cleanup." So,
I advised that they should seal off the
interview of John Walker, Lind, and use
the information only for national
security and intelligence gathering
purposes, but not for criminal
prosecution.
Meanwhile, pictures were circulating
worldwide by that time of this guy
naked, bound to a board with duct tape,
blindfolded, hands tied in front of his
genitals. It was pretty clear this guy
was not being treated well. In fact,
this looked very much like what we saw
years later at Aboot Grave.
Today I'm announcing the filing of
criminal charges against John Walker
Lind.
>> The attorney general Ashcraftoft was
into these very flashy press conferences
and he held one saying that they were
going to be filing charges against John
Walker Lind. and a reporter asked if he
had been permitted to have a lawyer and
Ashcraftoft said,
>> "I think it's important to understand
that uh the subject here is entitled to
choose his own lawyer and to our
knowledge has not chosen a lawyer at
this time."
This afternoon, a grand jury in the
Eastern District of Virginia returned a
10count indictment against Walker Lind.
>> A couple weeks later, again, he was
asked about the treatment of John Walker
Lind and he said that John Walker Lind's
rights,
>> including his rights not to be not to
incriminate himself and to be
represented by council, have been
carefully, scrupulously honored. So, I
felt like he's flat out lying.
Any human can read the newspaper and see
pictures of this guy being tortured.
>> And his defense argues that his
statements to the FBI are unreliable
because he made them after being held
for two or three days in this metal
container.
>> And more information was coming out.
>> Blindfolded, his hands and feet
painfully bound to a stretcher.
>> That he had a bullet in his leg that he
was being held in a box. I was getting
very much a vibe from my boss to drop it
and I was concerned there was an ethical
violation here. We still have not
resolved this with the criminal division
about how to deal with it.
>> And she said,
>> I want you to close
>> I want you to close the file.
>> It was clear that there was another plan
that was being put into place and it was
to prosecute this guy and make an
example out of him. He's accused of
conspiring to murder American citizens,
supporting terrorists, and supplying
services to the Taliban.
>> The government was now filing a criminal
complaint against this guy. He was the
first terrorism suspect to be prosecuted
after 9/11 and there was literally a
national hysteria around the case.
>> He tried to kill American troops
>> 1950s. What he did would have been
called treason and he would have been
sentenced to death.
>> He's a traitor. He should have been
>> two and two didn't add up till 4 until
March. The prosecutor in the John Walker
Lind criminal case, the case I advised
against bringing, contacted me directly
and he said, "As you know, um there is a
federal court discovery order for all
justice department correspondents
related to the interrogation of the
American Taliban, John Walker Lind. and
I have two of your emails and I wanted
to make sure I have everything.
And I knew I had written way more than
two emails. So immediately I became very
concerned. And you know, I went upstairs
and I'm like, I'm going to straighten
this out because I know the file was
like an inch thick.
And I went and looked in the file, the
hard copy file, and there were two
pieces of paper in there.
I mean, there was a fax cover sheet and
two very innocuous emails,
and I had not I felt like I was going to
be physically ill.
I consulted with a colleague of mine who
was a very seasoned attorney on the
verge of retirement. He worked in the
ethics division with me and he looked at
the file and said very matterofactly,
"This file has been purged."
And I thought, what? We're the
government. Like, we're prosecuting
Enron and Arthur Anderson right now for
destruction of evidence and obstruction
of justice. What do you mean it's been
purged?
The stuff in that file was very damning
because it said that the FBI had
committed an ethical violation in its
interrogation of John Walker Lind. And
if that confession could not be used at
trial, that was central to trying him.
They would have no case.
I called tech support. I'm like, "Look,
is there any way to get any of this
stuff back? It's really important." She
said that there was. And we were able to
recover 14 emails that had the substance
of what happened.
And I wrote a memo to my boss and said,
"I don't know why they weren't in the
file." And I made a copy of that memo
with the attachments in case it
disappeared again. And I gave it to my
boss
and she said, "Why weren't these emails
in the file?" And it felt like a
rhetorical question. And I said, "Look,
I don't know what's going on here, but
this is not right. And you know it, and
I'm giving my two weeks notice. I'm
resigning." I think people very high up
at justice wanted to cover up the fact
that the ethics office at the justice
department didn't want to follow the
rules and we're not going to follow the
rules and we're going to conceal this
from a court of law.
I could not live with myself knowing
that another
human being could be put to death
because I kept my mouth shut.
>> Michael is a Newsweek magazine
investigative reporter. Michael
>> one morning I heard Michael Isikov
saying,
>> "Well, the department says John Walker
Lind was never represented by council
and has never taken that position."
And I picked up the phone and I called
him
and I said, "You're wrong. I don't know
who's feeding you the this line of crap,
but it's completely wrong and I have the
emails to prove it."
And I went to a local kinkos
and I faxed him the emails.
He said he would write an article about
it. And he asked if I wanted to be
quoted in the article. And I said,
"Wouldn't that be a big red flag
pointing right at me?" And he said,
"Yeah." And I said, "Well, then no. I
don't want to be quoted." A lot of
whistleblowers, that's why they report
anonymously. They don't want to get in
trouble for it. But then my emails that
I had sent to him were published in full
on Newsweek's website with my name.
[Music]
I decided I had had enough. The agency
wasn't what it had been before September
11th. So I resigned and truly did not
look back.
And then I got a job with the uh Senate
Foreign Relations Committee and in that
job I got a call once from a journalist.
He had developed information that the
CIA was misusing its formal agreement
with the State Department to provide
cover by putting people who had been
involved in the torture program
undercover so that their names couldn't
be exposed in the press. So I wrote a
letter to the agency asking for
clarification.
Something like six weeks passed and
finally a colleague of mine came in the
office and said, "Uh, hey, you got a
response from the CIA uh to your
letter." I said, "I haven't seen any
response." He said, "Well, they
classified it top secret SCI, sensitive
compartmented information, and I wasn't
cleared for top secret SCI in that
Senate job." I said, "Well, what' the
letter say?" He said, "The letter says
to go [__] yourself."
And so I thought, "Wow, they're still
mad." And then my book came out and that
really made him mad.
>> His new book is The Reluctant Spy: My
Secret Life in the CIA's War on Terror.
Why would you keep doing the torture if
you if you if you got information that
you thought was
>> because I think people were panicked at
the time and they just couldn't bring
themselves to stop in case that
information came out. In the case of
Khaled Shake Muhammad and the third
prisoner who was waterboarded, Nashi, uh
it turned out that the information they
provided was not true. They they simply
provided what they thought the
interrogator wanted to hear to stop the
water boarding.
I've applied for every job I can think
of. Everything from grocery stores to
Toys R Us to Starbucks. You name it,
I've applied there. Haven't gotten even
a an email or a call back.
I'll be honest with you, I really miss
working. And so regardless of what the
job is, I'm going to be happy. I think
just passing 8 hours a day.
There were things I said in that book
that really bothered them. And I used a
lot of true names in the book, too.
People who weren't undercover.
I wanted to be on the record as saying
that I thought they were wrong.
[Music]
This was the wrong thing to do. This is
something that the that the US
government and the CIA should not be
involved in.
And a lot of people at the CIA disagree
with me. And I don't care. Not anymore.
I don't care.
when he's awake inside the house. You
know, it's almost an obsession.
[Music]
>> Ruby
put
>> you know he's always on the computer
he's always on the phone
>> there's really no moment of normaly
inside the house
the kids know nothing about what's going
on and uh I try and just protect them
and give John the space to do what he
needs to do
he does put on I think a really good
optimistic case,
but I know it bothers him deep down.
>> We're in the middle of what are called
SIPA hearings. Stands for the classified
information procedures act. We have
identified 100 maybe documents that are
classified that we believe are um
critical to my ability to defend myself.
Ultimately, in this case, Judge Brinkman
makes a determination as to what will
actually be admissible and relevant at
trial before a jury of his peers.
So, it's a critical phase.
>> The judge is going to come down on one
side or the other or maybe somewhere in
the middle. So, um I'm I'm serious when
I say I've read every one of these
documents and I can't defend myself
without them.
In the very beginning,
it would not be untruthful to say that I
felt suicidal.
I gave serious thought one day to
jumping in front of a subway train.
That's how that's how
how depressed I was and how hopeless I
felt.
>> Hello.
In my very first meeting with my
attorneys, they told me that if I took a
plea, my bill would probably be
somewhere in the $50,000 to $100,000
range. But they said if you elect to go
to trial, we're talking about a bill
that's going to be closer to $500,000.
So, here we are. My bill is already a
million. And if we go all the way
through trial, they told me to expect it
now to be as much as $2 million.
I can't pay that kind of money.
>> We don't need that anymore.
>> I don't know how I'll ever have that
kind of money to pay that bill.
[Music]
>> I knew that the White House and Hayden
had placed themselves above the law.
instead of choosing to follow the
Constitution, they had chosen to not
follow the Constitution. That they were
now in violation of the oath that they
took to support and defend and for the
president to also protect.
I blew every whistle there was
internally.
Early 2002, I'm a witness for this 911
congressional investigation. I gave them
incredibly classified information that
was given to me.
And what's important to understand is
not only did I share everything I knew
about thinth thread, I also was given
information during this time period.
Information that NSA had, information
that had been shared with the proper
authorities,
what's called national command
authorities
could have stopped 911.
I shared all that with the committee.
primmaaccia, al-Qaeda, and associative
movement information that would have
gone a long ways to rolling up the plot.
It was in the database. It was there.
No one knew it was there because the
systems they had in place were abysmal.
NSA had abysmally failed the nation.
Now, I was charged with putting together
the statement for the record to find out
everything we could about what NSA knew,
should have known, or could have known
prior to 911.
And I was given some extraordinary
information as a result of that. the
team.
That information was put into the
statement for the record, the draft.
And then while I was in England on
another assignment, got this frantic
phone call saying, "Tom, we've been
taken off the effort." I said, "Why?
When you come back, you'll have to find
out."
They did not want to tell the truth to
Congress.
So, as soon as I got back, I was pulled
aside. In no uncertain terms, I was
told, "Be careful. They're looking for
leakers. This was not leakers for the
press. They were looking for leakers to
the congressional 9/11 investigations.
>> They're in violation of FISA. They're in
violation of the Fourth Amendment.
They're now engaged in an active cover
up
at the highest levels. I knew that I had
been tagged as someone who was a threat
to their ability to keep from Congress
what they knew about 9/11. And in fact,
there was an edict that went out from
the highest levels of NSA through the
deputy director to bury all the critical
truth about what NSA actually knew about
911 and never let any investigator ever
get their hands on it. Period.
So, you know, here I am seeing all this
the massive fraud, waste, and abuse. I
had blown all the whistles I knew per
statute. Fall that all to the tea.
Nothing had happened. It was clearly
Congress institutionally had become
complicit. The primacy of national
security was now trumping the
Constitution.
And so I made a faithful decision in
February of 2006
to make contact anonymously with a
reporter
detailing with her over a series of
mailings and I was doing so in an
encrypted fashion for a period of a
year. An article was written by her in
which for the first time as public
revealed the existence of a legal
alternative to the secret program called
thinthread. The set of people that knew
about the secret program whether they
read into it or not was very very small.
They began to target anybody associated
with the program even if they were
peripheral. I had been told by very
wellplaced sources that Cheney
personally said to the Department of
Justice, "Find and fry the leakers.
Whoever, I don't care. Make an example
of them. Burn them."
So, I get a phone call from a former
colleague, Kirk Web, say, "Tod, we need
to meet." And we met and he proceeded to
tell me that we had just been raided by
the FBI.
And I knew sitting there in that tavern
I was next because they were asking them
about me. I was now clearly the primary
target. Somehow I had become I was
considered the ring leader. That somehow
I was now the source.
It was just a matter of time. It was not
if it was when I had already been put
under extraordinary electronic
surveillance. I was also physically
tailed, physically surveiled. It was not
unusual at all to see two unmarked cars
at the end of the street.
So, the morning of 28 November 2007,
I'm getting ready to go to work. It's
just after 7:00. about to get into my
car
[Music]
and there's this very very loud knock on
the door.
Spouse was there. She was about to take
our son Zachary to middle school. I I
mean I sit here right now with the look
on her face.
They served me with a warrant,
but I did cooperate with them. That was
for like eight and a half, nine hours.
And they're asking questions, and they
had one of the FBI agents simply taking
notes.
Your Miranda rights are read to you.
They said, "Anything you say will and
can be used against you."
It ultimately was. So every room had
like a number in it just kind of
hanging. And they began to go through
everything. It was clear that they were
looking for headers or anything that
showed, you know, classification stamps.
And they actually removed several books
that were actually listed on the warrant
that included James Ryzen's State of War
book
that they actually uh that became
evidence. Words and phrases. And those
words and phrases would have included
the secret program uh that that I had
disclosed to the congressional
investigators. My understanding is
sometimes they will catalog things and
they will actually and then at least but
they didn't do that. I mean, it's had
stuff everywhere
cuz this is it's so off it. Every single
drawer
and cabinet.
They were down here looking at the pots
and pans. They reaching behind here.
They were underneath the sink, seeing
your entire life and sort of the daily
things that you you have in your life
and the things you touch. and now
they're being touched by
FBI agents because you're up to no good
and they're inside all of your cabinets.
And
yeah, there's there's a distinct
more than just a passing feeling of of
being violated.
All these questions. You going to end up
indicting me? What charges will they
file? What else will happen to me?
I was separated not long after this and
ended up having to move out of the
house. Um,
and did so in January of of
2008 and was living
was living north of here for almost the
next year.
So
yeah, that's part of the price you pay
is
it's
that evening I got a phone call to
report to NSA special HR department and
they suspended my clearance. I had to
turn on my badges. They suspended my
clearance, put me on administrative
leave.
[Music]
They ended up charging me with three
counts of espionage.
And it turned out that they had been
investigating me since the ABC News
interview in 2007.
They've had it out for me since December
of 2007. In part because of the official
work I was doing as a senior staff
member of a of a congressional oversight
committee and they're trying to make it
look as though I provided classified
information to the press.
>> I worry very much about John's
well-being, not just on a professional
level, on a personal level, on a human
level. It's hard for any single
individual, no matter how strong you
are, to deal with this and come out on
the other side of it intact.
[Music]
When we were in our last hearing called
the SIPA hearing, the government asked
for what they call a a rule four
conversation. I had never heard of this.
But rule four, wherever this is written,
allows the government to have an inc
camera conversation with the judge.
Meaning, they get a private conversation
about the case with the judge without
the the defense attorneys or the
defendant being present and we we don't
have the right to know what that
conversation is about. So, they had one
of these in camera rule four
conversations. The next thing I knew,
the judge came out and ruled against us
on all of our motions.
So, where we thought we were going to
have this uh declassified information
with which I could defend myself,
at the end of the day, we ended up with
nothing.
>> And there are ps out there that would be
fine. I would bless a plea for one year
of jail to a making false statement
charge. That's a tack on charge that
they put on every indictment. It's very
different to plead guilty to an
intelligence identity protection act
charge and be the second person in the
entire country who's ever plead guilty
to that.
>> My defense attorneys claimed that they
reached out to the prosecution
unofficially just to see if there was
any room for negotiation. And so
within 24 hours, we had this offer on
the table.
For people who are facing such
lifealtering decisions, they deserve the
straight dope on what's going on.
>> We are going to Virginia.
>> I'm looking for the address which I have
here.
>> One of the lawyers, the one that I like
and respect the most, leaned over and
said, "If you were my brother, I would
tell you to take the deal. You're not
going to get a better deal. And if you
don't take it, you're going to risk
spending most of the rest of your life
in prison.
>> I feel like we're about to stage an
intervention, which is really pathetic
that it's come to this. But he emailed
one of the criminal defense attorneys
that, you know, I'm having second
thoughts about saying I take the plea
last night. I told him, "Unless you
convey that to the lead attorneys, they
can go into this hearing in exactly one
hour from now and say, "Judge Brinkma,
no need to have the hearing. Our guy has
decided to plead guilty."
>> I thought about it all weekend.
I changed my mind several times
and then we had a hard deadline of 5:00
yesterday afternoon.
Finally at 6:00 they called me and said
it's time to fish or cut bait.
I I have two
choices right now. It seems to me one is
to fire them and find somebody else and
the other is to take this deal.
>> Okay.
>> They said that they will mount the most
vigorous defense in court that they can,
but they believe that I'll lose and I'll
get six to 12 years.
I feel like they've come to the
conclusion that
it doesn't matter that there are
different layers of cover because
nobody's going to care. And so,
>> okay, well, let me tell you, let me tell
you why it matters. Because this is why
they're they want you to bargain on this
count. They know that they are weak.
They know that IIPA is written so
narrowly that it's virtually impossible
to prove.
>> We talk about this all night long.
That's why I come home. I take the kids
to school. I come back and I sleep on
the couch for an hour because I've been
up all night long. She doesn't make
enough money to support our household.
We can borrow enough for 2 years
to keep her going,
probably without filing for bankruptcy.
But if I if I were were to be found
guilty and got more than two years, I
mean, we think we're ruined now. We'd be
ruined permanently after that.
>> L
>> and I'm missing, too. But
>> Tom Drake thinks I should fight it. And
you know, in my gut, I want to fight it,
but I have kids
and I just can't risk
them losing me for 6 to 12 years.
>> Uh, good afternoon. I just have a brief
statement. Uh,
John Keryaku is a loyal American who
loves his country deeply. He served for
many years in the CIA as an agent in
challenging and
often dangerous assignments.
And nothing that happened today in this
plea does not diminish in any way the
value of his service to the country or
the contributions he made
to the security of our nation.
>> Are you at least happy that it's
involved?
[Music]
>> Obviously I'm persona nangrada within
the government. you don't have a
security clearance
and so I'm unemployed.
So I did look for work. I spent a lot of
time looking for work.
I applied for a a part-time position
with Apple
and several months later I actually got
a phone call.
You know, I ended up working at an Apple
store in the greater DC area as an
expert.
[Music]
A number of retaliatory steps were
taken. I was made the target of a
federal criminal leak investigation.
I was referred by the Justice Department
to the state bars in which I'm licensed
as an attorney. It is a big deal. If
you're referred to the bar, you could
lose your license to practice law. They
referred me based on a secret report to
which I did not have access.
A justice department investigator called
my new law firm, a private law firm
where I worked and told them that they
had just hired a criminal,
that I was going to steal attorney
client files and that they should really
think about firing me. So they put me on
administrative leave which was paid
briefly and then
suddenly they stopped paying me. So I
applied for unemployment.
Soon afterwards the investigator called
me and started asking questions about
the Newsweek article.
He grew very antagonistic.
He said, "Did you ever send emails to
Michael is the cuff and he's like, "If
you don't tell me, you we're going to
search your computer." And I'm like,
"Well, that you know, you know what? I I
have to go. I'll call you back later."
And instead, I called a lawyer. I mean,
I was devastated. I lost my dream job
and what I wanted to do. I was
incredibly anxious because I felt like I
was now under attack and under
investigation. I also have multiple
sclerosis um which is a neurological
disease exacerbated by stress.
>> Part of the purpose of doing what
they've been doing for the last several
years
is to destroy you.
>> The stress is hard to describe.
information.
>> They leak information, for example, to
the press that puts you in the worst
possible light.
>> The Justice Department called me a
traitor and a turncoat in the New York
Times.
>> You're not loyal. You're not a good
American. You're a terrorist
sympathizer.
>> 10 felony charges filed against a former
exam.
>> It was at top of news at 6:00. It was
the top of news at 11 locally. And it
was at the top of news the next morning.
>> Co-workers would not talk to me. And a
few of them said, "Do not call me at
work.
>> You betrayed your country. Where there's
smoke, there's fire. You did something.
Why would the government raid your
house? Why would they do that?
>> I was caught up in this Kafka-esque
nightmare.
>> I have to try to protect my children
from from being exposed to it. I've got
the FBI surveilling me on and off for
the last seven months. They followed us
grocery shopping. They followed me into
church on Sunday morning." and sent FBI
agents to sit behind me in church and
watch me. I had neighbors calling me
saying, "You know, there's a a car at
the end of the block and the guy's
looking at your house with binoculars."
One woman who was parked and and just
watching my children. And I went up to
her van and I knocked on the window and
I said, "What do you want?" And she kind
of got nervous and put the car in gear
and took off.
>> I was trying to be honest. I was trying
to do things by the book. And yet I'm
the one who ends up having to hire a
team of lawyers.
>> You have to mortgage your house. You
have to empty your bank account. I went
from making well over 150,000 a year to
a quarter of that.
>> The groups that I thought would want to
get involved in helping me like the ACLU
did not. So I was paying for private
counsel um on my own. The cost alone
financially, never mind the personal
cost, is approaching $1 million in terms
of lost income, expenses, and other
costs that I incurred.
>> I was told that I was blacklisted.
>> My wife resigned because the agency
threatened her with a security
investigation and so both of us have
been out of work for 7 months at this
point. It's surreal is the word.
A couple of weeks ago, my wife and I had
this conversation. It was on a Sunday
night, and she said, "We can't afford
food for the next week." And she said,
"I don't know what we're going to do."
So, very reluctantly, we went to the
county welfare office. We explained our
situation and they said, "Yeah, you guys
qualify for everything. Food stamps,
Medicaid, cash payments, job training,
everything.
[Music]
The pregnancy in a way kept me really
grounded like the kids did
because I knew there was something so
much larger than all this crap that was
going on.
It was something I could focus on
protecting and somehow by protecting the
baby I could protect myself in some kind
of way.
I had gone
to work. I was still I had gone into
Hawk and Stella Field and Wood, the law
firm where I worked. And my boss
told me, he's like, "You should know
that
the managing partner in New York and
Agent Powell are walking around the
office right now."
And Agent Powell had said, "Something
really big is going to happen. It sounds
like you're going to be arrested
tonight."
And so I
was just
so scared by that. And um
nighttime it was the worst time for me.
That's when I always kind of had my
night demons,
you know, and I'm imagining doing the
perp walk in front of all the
neighborhood moms and, you know, having
to go in the police car and be booked.
all of this stuff would really
like be in my mind and I couldn't turn
it off. And um yeah, I just woke up the
next morning and my night gown was just
is totally just blood everywhere.
And I just
I just knew that
I knew I wasn't pregnant anymore.
[Music]
You know, sometimes if I'm driving
around the area and there's an Orthodox
church, if I notice some cars in the
parking lot, I go over to church, sit
through the service, light a candle, and
go on my way. It I I take strength in
that. It comforts me.
One thing that's very important to me is
the personal story of of a 20th century
saint in the Orthodox Church, St.
Necarios.
St. Necdarios went through his entire
life trying to correct or rebut lies
that had been told about him by people
who coveted his office. He was
personally ruined by these rumors.
He was stripped of his position. He was
demoted. He lost everything. And he
never he never accused anyone. He
forgave them and he moved on with his
life.
[Music]
Thank you.
The only place left, the only other
check on the secret side of government,
the only other place to begin to
articulate what was really at stake both
for me personally as American, but what
was what were the larger stakes for
America was the court of public opinion.
And the person that led that effort was
Justin Raak.
I read about Tom's case in the newspaper
and I was immediately alarmed. Clearly a
line had been crossed because as
unmercifully
as a Bush administration treated me, at
least I was never prosecuted. and here
they were going to prosecute someone.
I stayed up that night. I started an
op-ed about the difference between
leaking and whistleblowing and I
submitted it and luckily the Los Angeles
Times published it. I often will write
about something and put it out there
almost as a beacon
um
for someone for someone to grasp onto.
>> She not only got who I was as a
whistleblower, she realized what was at
stake because she herself had
experienced what it meant to be on the
receiving end of a government who wanted
to punish her for simply standing up and
telling the truth. I needed to do an
educational campaign. I needed to do a
whistleblower reprisal complaint because
he had gone through proper channels and
complained to the inspector general. And
this was the ultimate retaliation. They
sold him down the river and gave his
name to the Justice Department to
prosecute. We had an article by Jane
Mayor of the New Yorker who did an
indepth long form investigative
journalistic piece.
>> The government says he betrayed his
country
>> and that was followed the next week by a
60 minutes piece and then there were
editorials by the LA Times and the
Washington Post saying that Tom Drake is
a whistleblower and it's ridiculous to
be using the Espionage Act against him.
That media was, I think, a saving grace.
>> Federal prosecutors today dropped nearly
all of the charges against Thomas Drake,
the former US intelligence official who
walked out of the Baltimore courthouse
today, had been charged under the
Espionage Act with mishandling sensitive
information. It's a high-profile failure
for the Justice Department, which is
cracking down on government leaks.
You know, I'm not sure anymore exactly
who the good guys are.
So much has changed since September 11th
in our country that what a decade ago
would have been insanity in terms of
policy is now the norm.
And it's as though
if you don't buy into the policy,
you're an enemy.
>> Dad.
>> Yep.
>> There's Batman eats a hot dog and
there's hot dog eats Batman.
>> There's also one that Cookie Monster
eats a cookie.
>> This past weekend, news came out of
General Petraeus's affair. More news
followed that his alleged girlfriend may
have had classified information on her
computer.
And then the FBI issues a statement
saying that it's not a criminal
investigation. Well, just a week ago,
they charged a translator in Bahrain
with two counts of espionage uh for
sending a classified document to
Stanford University's archives. Uh if
this woman had classified information on
her computer, she obviously had to have
gotten it from Petraeus. Well, why
aren't they being charged with
espionage?
Okay, let's see what I have here.
phone
glasses cuz I'm blind.
Okay, in this case it looks like if
you're a general and you're buddies with
the president or if you're the
girlfriend of the general, you're going
to get a pass.
[Music]
>> If you're a nobody, you're going to go
to jail on something. Whether it's an
espionage act count or some reduced
penalty, you're going to go to jail.
>> Good to see you.
>> Thanks for the speech.
>> You don't have a dollar. It's okay. It
was okay. There was one line where it
said like something like this has been
mentally hard on my
kids or something. I forgot to add in
and my wife.
>> Yeah.
>> See my kids grow up.
The 23rd annual Joey Callaway Award for
Civic Courage is hereby presented to
John Kuryaku,
anti-torrture advocate on the Ramparts.
In recognition of his stand against
using torture to extract information
from government prisoners,
his public disclosure that torture,
including waterboarding, is official
policy, not a rogue event, as the
government claimed. his leadership as
the first CIA officer to confirm and
then condemn this illegal torture
policy.
There's a rumor that they might just
shackle me and take me away tomorrow.
Yeah. So, I'm going to take off my uh
crucifix and my wedding ring before I
leave for the courthouse. I don't know.
Send me to some p Yeah. Send me to some
prison someplace.
Don't worry.
Okay.
No, don't be. Don't be.
When we first told the kids that I was
going to have to leave for a couple of
years, Max took it hard. He cried a lot.
>> Okay. You want this blanket?
>> Tell you why. Cuz my hand feels all
stiff when I move it.
>> Okay. He was upset that I was not going
to be around for his birthday.
>> I'm going to miss his first communion.
Cold today.
19°.
>> Hi. Good morning.
They don't want me to give a statement.
I said, I just want to thank people. So,
I'm going to I'm going to thank people.
>> Today's sentence should be a reminder to
every individual who works for the
government who comes into the possession
of closely held sensitive information
regarding the national defense or the
identity of a covert agent that it is
critical that that information uh remain
secure.
John is the only CIA agent who will be
going to prison with respect to the
torture program and he didn't torture
anybody. He is also the only CIA agent
going to prison for leaking something to
the press when we've had numerous top
level disclosures of classified
information including sources and
methods to Hollywood for the production
of the movie Zero Dark 30 and no one
seems to have a problem with that.
This morning I uh I was sentenced to 30
months uh in prison for a crime to which
I had pleaded guilty. I want to say that
I come out of court positive, confident,
and optimistic. I would like to thank
several
[Music]
Today I have an audience of one and it's
Barack Obama.
We're at the point now where this is
between Barack Obama and me. He's the
only person who can help me if he's so
inclined and I have to try to reach him
today.
Stand by.
>> 15.
Coming up, the first CIA officer ever
sentenced for leaking classified
information. Why does he consider that
to be a badge of honor? And rare
treasures from President Kennedy in our
studio before they hit the auction
block.
>> We want to start this half hour with a
former CIA officer who sent us 30 months
behind bars. The first to ever be sent
to jail for leaking classified secrets.
We're going to talk to him exclusively
in a moment. But first, with the
backstory, here's NBC's Andrea Mitchell.
led investigators to Mr. Kuryaku who
then admitted in court under oath that
he knowingly intentionally outed the
identity of this corporate agent.
>> Kuryaku has portrayed himself as a
whistleblower for disclosing the Bush
administration's controversial water
boarding techniques.
>> And John Kuryaku is with us exclusively.
John, good morning. It's good to see
you.
>> Good morning. Thanks for having me.
>> Depending on who you are, you look at
this case differently. Some people say
you betrayed your former colleagues in
order to raise your media profile,
hoping to sell books and to get a
consulting business going. Others say
you were a whistleblower. You spoke out
and now you're being wrongly prosecuted.
You say you wear this conviction like a
badge of honor.
>> I do. I wear this conviction as a badge
of honor because this conviction is not
about leaking. This case was about
torture from the very beginning. Let me
just stop you right there because you
acknowledged you pleaded guilty and you
admitted that you identified a CIA
officer who was in fact covert. That is
against the law. You don't you don't
disagree with that.
>> No. And I and I should never have done
that. That was a terrible mistake.
>> In fact, in 2007, you told MSNBC you
were coming forward then because you
thought that the agency had gotten quote
a bum wrap on waterboarding. That's
somebody who's defending these
practices, not denouncing them. I was
relying on what the CIA had told CIA
officers inside the building that these
methods were effective. That turned out
to be a lie.
>> And you've admitted not just to the
leaking of the one name, but you also
acknowledged giving classified
information to yet a second reporter.
Did you ask these journalists, hey, what
are you going to do with this
information?
>> Well, let me let me correct you on one
thing. The reporter came to me with the
name and said, "Can you talk to
>> I think specifically the charges said
that you disclosed the connection of
that officer to a classified operation."
And yet in a recorded FBI interview a
year ago, you said you knew that this
officer was always
[Music]
final. You disclose the name of this
officer to this journalist. The
journalist in turn passed it to a
defense investigator. A picture of this
officer ended up in the jail cell of a
terror suspect. How do you feel about
that?
>> Stay right there. Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. Thanks for taking
a
>> You don't think I helped myself?
I'll just keep my fingers crossed. See
what happens.
We've never used the word prison with
the children.
>> We told them that, you know, I've been
involved in this fight with the FBI for
the last year. And I said,
"Unfortunately, I lost."
And so because I lost, I'm going to have
to go to Pennsylvania for 2 years to
teach bad guys how to get their high
school diplomas.
>> And when I finish that contract, I'm
going to come home. We're going to be
together again as a family, and
everything's going to be back to normal.
How are your days at school?
>> Good. Good.
>> Good.
>> So guys, this is the last time I'm going
to pick you up from school for a while.
>> I wish my daddy was with me all the
time.
>> You guys will have a good vacation this
year.
>> Yeah, but you're not going to be with
us.
Why?
Wish you won,
>> daddy.
>> Yeah.
>> I wish you won.
>> What? Honey,
>> I wish I won, too.
>> Hey, Max.
>> You want to play in the backyard?
>> Okay. You have a jacket?
I'm hoping the actual day of my
departure is going to be as normal a day
for the kids as possible.
>> I think most of these mess the blue part
in the sky.
>> I don't want the kids to be disrupted in
any way that day.
>> I don't want there to be lots of tears
and you know, oh my god, what are we
going to do for the next two years? I
don't want any of that. I want them to
think, "Okay, dad's going to go. He's
going to work and we'll see him on the
weekends and everything's going to be
okay.
>> I got it. I got it.
>> Dad
get
Let me see.
>> You gave it a little You gave it a
little scrape, honey.
>> Yeah.
I am.
[Music]
Man, I'm tired.
>> How are you?
>> I'm all right.
>> He doesn't look like he's telling the
truth. I never get to do anything.
Hey, I've got an idea. Let's play drive
the bus. I'll go first.
I think it's going to take a long time
before people realize what a mistake we
made with this torture program.
I think it's going to be 20, 30, 40
years before people say we tortured
people in this country.
What were we thinking?
I have great fears for the future of the
republic.
Because if the trend line continues, a
national security regime, a secrecy
regime cannot coexist with a
constitutional democracy. Something has
to give.
>> Only 10 people in American history have
been charged with espionage for leaking
classified information. Seven of them
under Barack Obama.
The effect of the charge on a person's
life, being viewed as a traitor, being
shunned by family and friends, incurring
massive legal bills, is all a part of
the plan of forcing the whistleblower
into personal ruin to weaken him to the
point where he will plead guilty to just
about anything to make the case go away.
I know the three espionage charges
against me
one of the Obama seven.
I think the government's going to launch
an investigation. I think they're going
to say, "I've committed grave crimes.
I've, you know, violated the Espionage
Act." They're going to say, you know,
I've I've uh aided our enemies.
>> Disclosure of this kind of highly
classified material gives our terrorist
enemies a playbook for our activities
designed to thwart.
>> The longer the Snowden saga drags on, so
do the questions about the surveillance
programs. I don't think anything about
this is something the White House wants
to deal with. The government is
desperate to not deal with the actual
content of those disclosures.
>> Why is the government spying on its own
people?
>> Our concern is that they have grabbed
these phone calls and grabbed these
emails and have the temptation to listen
to them and read them whether they have
the authority to or not. The US
government has routinely violated the
constitutional protections afforded its
own citizens while disregarding the
internal integrity of other states and
the fundamental rights of non US
citizens.
Some of the investigations began during
the Bush administration
as was the case with an essay
whistleblower Tom Drake. But espionage
act cases have been prosecuted only
under Obama.
You know, he's my only client um in jail
for this right now. And he completely
doesn't belong there. And he completely
gets how politicized this is. And
for me, um, as an attorney, I know I did
all I could for him. Um, but on a
personal level,
um,
it feels like a failure. I feel
like like I could have there's something
I could have done more.
In our history, it's been whistleblowers
who have made the difference. It's been
whistleblowers who have caused these
major cataclysmic changes in our
society.
And I I think freedom can win out over
fear.
Heat. Heat.
[Music]
Morning.
Heat.
[Music]
Heat. Heat.